The James Graham Leyburn Papers, 1902-1993 WLU.Coll.0288
Washington and Lee University, James G. Leyburn Library Special Collections and Archives
James Graham Leyburn Papers
1902-1993
Washington and Lee University, James G. Leyburn Library, Special Collections and Archives
Leyburn, James Graham
WLU.Coll.0288
10.5 Linear Feet
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Series 1 of this collection was given by Dr. Leyburn following his retirement from Washington and Lee University in 1972.
Biographical / Historical
James Graham Leyburn was born in Hedgesville, West Virginia, on January 17, 1902. He became a professor of sociology and Dean of the University at Washington and Lee in 1947 and held the post of Dean until 1956 continuing as Professor of Sociology until 1972. In the 1920s and 1930s Dr. Leyburn held professional positions at Hollins College, Princeton University, and Yale University. In 1943 he was engaged by the U. S. Government Foreign Economic Administration's Office of the Lend-Lease Administration to participate in a mission in South Africa.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains many materials relating to the South African mission. Dr. Leyburn saved a number of newspaper articles concerning South Africa which are contained herein. Reports on various industries and other aspects of South Africa are included. Also within this collection are an assortment of Dr. Leyburn's speeches, some of which address South Africa. The remainder of the speeches concern the future of Washington and Lee University.
Among the correspondence in this collection are letters concerning Yale, W&L, and South Africa. There are also letters to his family, including his sister Ellen. A number of reviews of Dr. Leyburn's books, The Haitian People and The Way We Lived, as well as Dr. Leyburn's own reviews of other books are included.
The more telling items of this collection are the numerous student comments that Dr. Leyburn preserved. A voluminous journal of his world travels provides for interesting reading as does the poetry written by John Alexander Graham. Includes one photograph of Leyburn and three other professors (Riegel, Barritt, and Myers).
Appended to this collection are three scrapbooks which provide a record of Dr. Leyburn's activities at W & L and afterward.
There are also Leyburn's musical compositions and diplomas.
South Africa; Haitians -- Social conditions; Haitians -- Economic conditions; Universities and colleges -- Faculty; Europe; Economic history; Voyages and travels; Photographs; Autobiography; Correspondence; Scrapbooks; Diplomas; Leyburn, Ellen Douglass; Washington and Lee University; United States. Foreign Economic Administration; Graham, John Alexander; Riegel, O. W. (Oscar Wetherhold)
- Series 1, 1925-1973; 7 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains many materials relating to his South African mission. Dr. Leyburn saved a number of newspaper articles concerning South Africa, which are contained herein. Reports on various industries and other aspects of South Africa are included. Also within this collection is an assortment of Dr. Leyburn's speeches, some of which concern South Africa. The remainder of the speeches concern the future of Washington and Lee University.
  Among the correspondence in this collection are letters concerning Yale, Washington and Lee University, and South Africa. There are also letters to his family, including his sister Ellen. A number of reviews of Dr. Leyburn's book, The Haitian People, as well as Dr. Leyburn's own reviews of other books are included.
  There are numerous student comments that Dr. Leyburn preserved as well as a voluminous journal of his world travels and the poetry written by John Alexander Graham. Includes one photograph of Leyburn and three other Washington and Lee professors (Riegel, Barritt, and Myers).
  Additionally, there are three scrapbooks which provide a record of Dr. Leyburn's activities at Washington and Lee and afterward.
  Scrapbooks; Photographs; South Africa; Speeches, addresses, etc., American; Correspondence; Washington and Lee University; Yale University
  - Control folder, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 0)
    This folder contains a biography of Dr. James G. Leyburn.
  - Leyburn's articles on Africa, "Native Farm Labor," "Disabilities of the Southern African Native," and "The White Man in New Africa." (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Articles on education including "The Education of a Southerner" and "A Plan for an Ideal College." (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
  - Articles on Haiti and the manuscript that was later extended and became THE HAITIAN PEOPLE. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Entry written by Dr. Leyburn for FUNK AND WAGNALLS STANDARD REFERENCE ENCYCLOPEDIA entitled "Negroes in the U.S." (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Numerous articles by Dr. Leyburn on religion (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Article: "The Scotch-Irish: An American Social Force," published by NEW SOCIETY in 1962. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous articles on culture including "Notes on American Culture." (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Book reviews written by Leyburn between 1961-65 for THE ROANOKE TIMES. (Box 1, Folder 9-15)
  - Book reviews written by Leyburn between 1944 and 1972 that appeared in periodicals (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Dr. Leyburn's correspondence concerning the abolishment of subsidized athletics which occured at Washington & Lee in 1954. (Box 1, Folder 17-19)
  - Clippings from newspapers, the RING-TUM PHI and THE ALUMNI MAGAZINE that deal with the athletic question at W & L. (Box 1, Folder 20-22)
  - University rebuttals to the aforementioned clippings and the introduction of "The Leyburn Plan." (Box 2, Folder 23, Folder 24)
  - Material from Dr. Leyburn's tenure as President of the Gamma Chapter of Virginia from 1962 to 1964. (Box 2, Folder 25-26)
  - Information about life at Washington and Lee during the 1960s (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Honorary degree candidate correspondence during Dr. Leyburn's time as Dean of the Faculty (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Various W & L programs of events including the program of the inauguration of President Fred Cole in 1961. (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Various issues of the student newspaper, THE RING-TUM PHI. (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Student papers collected by Dr. Leyburn (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Correspondence pertaining to Dr. Leyburn's tenure as Editor of SHENANDOAH, the literary magazine published by W & L, in 1959. (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Dr. Leyburn's diary, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Materials pertaining to Dr. Leyburn's book The Scotch Irish (Box 2, Folder 34, 36, 40)
  - Correspondence from Terence Hughes concerning the publication of The Scotch Irish (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Reviews of The Scotch Irish (Box 3, Folder 37-39)
  - Materials dealing with a conference on plantations in Puerto Rico in 1957 and the duPont Conference of 1961 (Box 3, Folder 40-42)
  - Honors College material (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Material on the history of Lexington, Virginia (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Miscellaneous papers and the KING JAMES BIBLE (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Dr. Leyburn's class lectures for Anthropology 101 and Sociology 303. (Box 4)
  - Dr. Leyburn's class lectures on the Greek and Latin Classics of Comparative Literature 202. (Box 5)
  - Dr. Leyburn's class lectures for Greek and Latin Classics, Religion and Society and General Sociology. (Box 6)
  - Dr. Leyburn's class lectures on General Sociology, class rolls for 1949-1971, and an autographed copy of Ellen Douglas Leyburn's SATIRIC ALLEGORY: MIRROR OF MAN. (Box 7)
- Series 2, 1987-1993; 3.5 Linear Feet
  This series includes correspondence, proofs, and reviews concerning Leyburn's book The Way We Lived. Correspondents include Kenneth Rockwell, Marshall Fishwick, Rupert Nelson Latture, Michael Barr, and Lon K. Savage. There are also photographs of Leyburn, his music programs, and notices of his death.
  Photographs; Correspondence; Composition (Music); Autobiography; Barr, Michael; Latture, Rupert Nelson
- Oversized materials, 1902-1974; bulk; 1 Files (Oversize 27)
  This series consists of James G. Leyburn's diplomas and certificates of distinction.
  Diplomas; Leyburn, James Graham